I cut my arm. Look at it.
- It's not healing.
- Do you mean...?
I'm staying hurt.
Don't you see?
The whole world becomes immortal.
And I'm mortal. I don't mend.
I'm normal again.
This, Captain, fascinates me.
- What makes you so different?
- I don't know.
And yet you're the only one left,
the only true human. So tell me,
what did you give them so long ago?
Why would he want you dead?
On the very day that no-one's dying?
Wish I knew.
Every time you turn up,
it always go wrong.
Where are you from?
Long ago and so far away.
(HUBBUB)
MAN: Harkness. Anyone?
Jack Harkness.
I'm looking forJack Harkness.
That's me.
Welcome to America, Mr Harkness.
There's your visa all stamped.
Grazie. I mean,
thank you very much, Inspector.
Hey, wait! Stop that man!
(WHISTLES PEEP)
Come on now.
You're not Jack Harkness.
The visa's mine.
It's what?
You'll find everything's in order.
The British consulate arranged for my
travel through the embassy in Rome.
That visa belongs to me.
Yes, sir.
Terribly sorry this happened, sir.
Take him away. Send him back home.
- There you are.
- Thank you.
You're still here.
I thought you'd be in the city by now.
Time to spare.
Waiting for the next boat to Manhattan.
I also am waiting for a boat.
Mine goes all the way
- back to Italy.
- Right.
That's what they do with thieves.
An interesting fact is they do it
also with people who forge visas.
Good eye.
- Why didn't you tell them?
- I wasn't sure.
Until that moment when you said,
"Why didn't you tell them?"
(CHUCKLES)
I'm on a kind of unofficial
official visit,
one part of the government
pretending to be another part.
You work for a government?
Look at me.
Do I look like a bureaucrat?
Never seen a man like you before.
More like a soldier.
Your English is good. Where did you learn?
We had a schoolmaster in the village.
He taught me.
I went to him every single day
because I always dreamt of coming here.
- What's the village?
- You wouldn't know it.
No-one ever does.
Tiny place on the Amalfi Coast.
And I mean, for certain,
right on the coast.
The whole place is holding its breath
on the edge of a cliff top.
If you look over,
hundreds of feet down to the sea.
Sounds beautiful. Why'd you ever leave?
New York. They have buildings here
taller than the cliff.
- I wanted to see that.
- You wait.
They've only just started building.
Years to come, they're going to have...
- What? They're going to have what?
- Never mind. What's your name?
Angelo Colasanto.
- La magia oscura!
- It's not magic.
Technology.
Sometimes they're indistinguishable.
Hey, hey, hey!
How does it work? Can I see it?
Hey, over here!
We just found this man's papers.
You can let him go.
We're going to Manhattan.
Who are you?
What do you want?
What do you want?!
(PHONE RINGS)
Rhys, call me, OK?
Mam, if you can, call me, OK?
Vera! Vera! Vera!
How many views have we got now?
Um, over five million.
People are setting up
memorial services for her too.
Just random people
who didn't even know her.
I just, um...
You got the footage
and that's going to make the difference.
But I've been meaning to say, I...
I know that that must have been...
I'm sorry.
I got ya.
No, really, Rex.
I really didn't even know her
that well, OK?
- But you did. You must have talked.
- Look, she...
she told me about her mother,
her ex-husband,
possibly something about
a brother or a sister.
I don't know, maybe not.
- The obituary says...
- Yeah. But what does it matter?
Hmm? Whoever she was, it's gone.
- I don't even know where she's from.
- The news is saying San Antonio.
Well, then, go Spurs!
Sorry.
I don't know how to help.
Except that...maybe her death
has changed things.
They'll shut down the camps.
No, they "paused" the camps.
That's all they're saying. Paused.
And while the politicians
are all denying everything,
those ovens are still out there,
waiting to burn.
- (DOOR OPENS)
- Jack!
- Gwen, you're back.
- Where's Jack?
Sorry about your dad.
- Did you hear any news?
- No, not really.
- Jack!
- He went outside.
- Jack?
- Hey!
I missed you.
I've been searching
through that Blessing stuff.
Listen, you've got to come down to
the car. I've got to show you something.
- Anything good?
- No, just stuff from back home.
Souvenir sort of thing.
Just you and me. Come on.
All right, stop your nagging.
Told you she missed me(!)
GWEN: Yeah, today would be good, Jack.
- (DOOR CLOSES)
- Bad day, Gwen?
Ohh!
(CAR HORN BLARES)
All right. OK.
(SHE SPEAKS ITALIAN)
I'm sorry. My Italian isn't so...
She's saying there is only one bed.
- (SPEAKS ITALIAN)
- Ah!
- I said I'll sleep on the floor.
- On the floor, yes.
(SHOUTING) He'll sleep on the floor.
(SPEAKS ITALIAN)
Come-a down to the shop any time.
Family butcher's is fine food.
And you are family now.
It's a good room.
And it's cheap.
You should save your money,
Angelo Colasanto.
Next couple of years,
earn as much as you can.
Save it all up
cos you're going to need it.
Bad times ahead.
Why, what's going to happen?
Oh! Oh, so many things.
Don't worry. It gets better.
Then it gets worse again.
You talk funny.
I'm a very funny man.
Scars.
You been in a lot of fights?
Sometimes you have to defend yourself,
you know?
People...say things.
(TYRES SQUEAL)
RADIO: Another non-stop hour
of music, weather...
(SWITCHES STATION)
...and allegations continue to surface
about procedures
at the new medical facilities.
But Oswald Danes has released
a statement in which he says
that a global emergency
calls for emergency measures
and he advocated a swift return
to the category policy.
Ah! I'm tied down.
- Why am I tied down?
- They're in my eyes.
- What?
The contacts. They're in my eyes.
Somebody's taken Anwen, Rhys,
my mother, the whole bloody family,
and they've said if I bring you,
they'll let them go unharmed.
Don't try moving.
You'll never get out of those knots.
My... My hands are asleep.
And my feet. You tied my feet?!
Of course I did, stupid.
Otherwise you'd get out of the car,
knock me out and turn the car around.
- Are you sure they have your family?
- I phoned 1 00 times.
There's no reply.
They... They've got them.
I want to talk to the lenses.
Look at me so I can talk to them.
Why do you always keep thinking
you can tell me what to do?
Pull over or look into the rear-view.
Just, please, let me talk to them.
Don't cock this up, OK?
Listen, whoever you are,
there's more than one way to play this.
Are you listening?
Yeah, there's a cursor. They're there.
You want me?
Let her family go
and I'll come to you alone.
- Tell them they can have me too.
- No, just me.
Let Rhys go, let Anwen go,
let her mother go free.
You guys, you know what?
Here I am. You got me.
GWEN: Nothing.
- Give them a minute.
- There's just nothing now.
- Maybe they're thinking about it.
- My mother's name is Mary.
Mary!
You've known me all this time
and you can't remember her name?
- All right, I'm sorry, OK?
- Yeah. Well, you should be,
because this is all your fault.
They want to kill you,
but why do they want to do that?
- I don't know.
- What have you done?
I don't know!
Well, you've done something,
haven't you?
Way back when
in that long bloody life of yours.
God, you've lived so long, you can't
remember half of it. Now you think.
Think! What the hell have you done?
JACK: I love this. I love weddings.
I don't believe in marriage.
So young, so handsome and so cynical.
ANGELO: Look at them.
What are their chances?
That's what makes it
so brave and wonderful...
making a promise and going forward.
It doesn't matter
what happens in the future.
Right now, it's real
and it happens and it's true.
You're Catholic, right?
Do you want to kneel down like that?
He doesn't hear me.
He doesn't hear you? Why?
You know why.
That's our padre. Wait here.
Forgive me, Father, for I have sinned...
so many times,
and that's just today.
It's been about...700 years
since my last confession.
Where do I start?
How about the triplets?
Or the naked circus?
Or that Sapphic leapfrog jamboree?
(CHUCKLES)
(CLEARS THROAT) No.
Let's just start with the sin of...
"Father Timothy sent me."
(LATCH CLICKS)
- You're Jack Harkness?
- Good to see you, Father.
I believe we're going to talk business.
The Volstead Act makes an exception
for sacramental wines.
And the brothers upstate
produce more than we can use.
The extra income feeds
a lot of widows and orphans, I'm sure.
Yes, I'm doing this entirely
for charity, every last cent.
It's not very good.
It's the blood of Christ, Angelo.
I'm sure it's good enough.
This is just a sample.
If you make enough profit,
we'll start delivering crates.
We should figure out a system.
Hey, what are you doing?
Who are you?
It's OK.
Let them take us, Angelo. It's OK.
Where are they taking us?
I don't know where. Just east.
Did they say get on the 1 0 going east?
Or on the eastbound 1 0 Freeway,
or what?
If they said highway,
they could be from back east.
If their grammar was wrong,
it could mean that English
is not their first language.
- I didn't notice anything wrong with it.
- You're Welsh.
You wouldn't notice
if the vowels were missing.
Button it!
Hey, you've got a gun, haven't you?
- You could smuggle it back here to me.
- It's gone.
They made me leave it behind.
Just give it up, Jack,
with all this planning, OK?
Because if there was a way out of this,
I can guarantee you
I would have thought of it.
Gwen, I shouldn't... There are reasons
I shouldn't even say this...
secrets...
but we could...we could find Anwen.
My wrist strap, it could find her.
We could save her.
What?
It's coded to my DNA.
And it resonates
to anything close to my DNA.
If you are using my daughter
as leverage, I swear to God,
- I will kill you myself.
- Listen to me.
If we recode it to your DNA,
then Anwen is a close match.
It would respond to her.
Like a tracker.
We could save her together.
We could rescue her.
You could do that?
You could do that recode thing?
Yes. A drop of your blood. A single cell
would do, but a drop would be easier.
- Let's do it.
- Pull over.
OK, let's do it. I'll have to untie you.
One hand forjust a second,
all right, Gwen?
I'd be saving Anwen.
You bastard.
Nice try.
GWEN: Oh, mm-hmm.
Whoever this is...they know you.
Phew!
So, Mr Harkness...and his acolyte.
- Yeah, and who are you?
- Your friend thinks he's funny.
He doesn't. He isn't. He's sorry.
This is Sal Maranzano.
- You were going to undercut my price.
- We found some untapped resource.
Rumour is you two are a pair of finocchi.
That's not a rumour. That's a boast.
And if you were really upset about
some small-time competition,
it'd already be hailing bullets.
So we're here for another reason.
I don't think so. Take 'em, kill 'em.
Give us a try, Maranzano.
You need men like us, off the grid.
Men who could never
be traced back to you.
So whatever it is you need, Sal,
no matter how dangerous it is,
no matter how strange it is,
you just found the right men.
There's a box in a warehouse
that needs to find its way
to another warehouse.
You can count on us.
You will not look in the box.
Sure thing.
You will swear...
on everything that is holy
you will deliver the box,
but you will not look inside.
I promise.
Then we got a deal.
Tomorrow night, Gallaco Wharf, Bay Five.
Get going. Get lost.
- You're running away?
- No.
That's mine! Wh...
What are you doing?
You're packing my things!
You need to go now. There's a plan.
And I'm not part of your plan?
Look at your hands. Not a scar on them.
I'm tougher than you.
Maranzano's people
have stumbled across something
they're not supposed to have.
I've got to stop them.
You made this happen?
You've planned this.
Since when?
Since you got on the boat to America?
Just get out of town, Angelo.
These people are bad.
You don't want to be on their list.
- Get far away.
- Who are you doing this for?
The government in England?
Or the other thing you said...Torchwood?
For the train. Go to the West Coast.
You're handsome enough.
Get into the movies.
- I'm not letting you send me away.
- Why?
Because you wouldn't know
how to get another man?
Because you're not brave enough?
You think I'm with you because it's easy?
- It's not easy, trust me.
- I know.
I hear the beads clicking
at night, Angelo.
Everything we do,
you ask for forgiveness afterwards.
That's just sex. Imagine if it was love.
What would he say then, your God?
What would he say if two men could love?
Oh! Oh, but no. No, that's impossible.
And if it's impossible,
then you can't stay with me.
You...
...you're an ass.
For a man who knows a lot of things,
huh, you're not so bright.
Think about it.
I grew up in a village with 200 people.
Only 200.
The sun would rise and the sun would set
over the same 200 people.
And that was it. That was my world.
And look at me now.
I'm a bootlegger in New York City
with you in my bed.
You think any of your little secrets
can change my life
more than it's already changed?
And yes, I...
I feel guilty about what we do.
It hasn't made me stop doing it.
Besides, I always hoped...
...if God is love,
maybe...
he loves me too.
That's blasphemy.
I think that's Christianity.
You're unpacking my things?
I've got this friend.
He's called The Doctor.
He explores the world...
...with a companion.
It looks nice.
Are you saying that I can stay?
Maybe.
Oh, Dio.
What's all this?
Ammonia refrigeration. Of course!
The best they could do in 1 927.
They said, "Don't look in the box."
- Yeah, right(!)
- What is it? What's inside?
Someone...
Someone way above Maranzano,
they found something, a weapon.
They told Maranzano to hold it
until after the next state election,
then ship it to Albany.
Maranzano doesn't know what he's got,
but he's terrified of it.
Can't say I blame him.
No. No, that's...
What?
Er, it's a parasite. Like a bug.
A parasite?
Tell me more about it.
Good man.
It's a species of brainspawn
treated as vermin on more than
1 50 planets that I know of.
And valued as dinner on one other.
It tastes like oysters.
- You did not.
- I had to be polite.
Now this part drills
into the brain of the host
and deposits its larvae there...
little worms,
sharp as needles,
pushing into the brain very slowly.
You go insane, but it takes years.
Franklin Roosevelt,
he's going to be elected governor
of New York this November.
But he wouldn't start making
the really crazy decisions
until his second term as president.
Result - America destabilises,
pulls out of the war, Germany rises,
the Third Reich triumphant, and there's
a whole new history sprawling out.
You mean someone is changing the future?
Destroying it.
Turning order into chaos
and feeding off the results.
Who would do such a thing?
These people above Maranzano.
They're just being used by someone
called The Trickster's Brigade.
Believe me, you don't wanna meet them.
What sort of men are they?
They're not men at all.
They're not even human.
OK. OK.
Ah, he likes you.
But it's cold, yeah? So it's safe?
- (HISSING)
- Oh, Dio!
Ha!
That'll dissolve it.
Ah!
So...the mission is complete.
We just saved the world, Angelo.
- And no-one will ever know.
- Then, did I pass?
Can I stay with you like The Doctor?
Learn all the secrets?
- (ALARM BELL RINGS)
- Here's one of the secrets...
run!
Quick. Come on, up. Let's go!
Hold it! Stop right there!
Take my hand.
Ah!
- Grab my hand!
- (CAPTAIN JACK PANTS)
- (GUNSHOT)
- No!
(DOG BARKS)
(WHISTLE BLOWS)
(THEY SHOUT OVER EACH OTHER)
All right, get him in there.
Go! Get him up the stairs. Step up.
Jack.
Meat cart's on the way for the other one.
You'd better take the main gate.
Off you go.
(SIREN WAILS)
(GASPS)
It's me.
- What do you mean?
- Well, it's me.
I caused this.
I made this...happen.
I knew Torchwood was toxic...
right from the moment I joined up,
the very first day, but...
I stayed.
- I'm glad you did.
- Hah! Stop being so nice.
We left nice behind 1 00 miles back.
I'm trying to be honest, OK?
Because do you know what
the worst thing is of all?
Out of all the shit we have seen,
all the bloodshed,
all the horror, do you know
what is worse than all of that?
I loved it.
I bloody loved it.
And I'd keep telling Rhys I was sorry
and I'd say to little Anwen, "I'm sorry,"
but I loved it so much.
I knew things no-one else knew
and, oh, I felt so special.
And when we lost people,
it was so, so big
and I could say it was worth it,
because the bigger it was,
the more important I was.
And the more people we lost...
...the more that meant I was a survivor
and I was better than them.
My God, this is all my fault.
And now they've got
my beautiful little girl
and I've wished this on her.
I used to think the same
about Torchwood...
That's what I'm saying.
Have you got what I'm saying to you, Jack?
What I'm saying is, no more.
Cos I know exactly what you're thinking,
Jack Harkness. I know it.
"She won't do this.
"Not really. Not my Gwen.
"No, Gwen, she can't hurt me.
"Gwen loves me.
She'd never hand me in."
Well, this is about my daughter.
And I swear, for her sake,
I will see you killed like a dog
right in front of me if it means
her back in my arms. Understood?
Understood.
And let me tell you,
now that I'm mortal,
I'm going to hang on to this
with everything I've got.
I love you, Gwen Cooper,
but I will rip your skin from your skull
before I let you take this away from me.
Understood?
Understood.
I feel like I know you now
better than I've ever done before.
Yeah.
- Right at the end.
- Mmm.
Right at the end.
Nice suit.
Look, it's all right. Don't panic.
- It's me. I'm the same man.
- I saw you.
I saw you get shot.
- I got better.
- You got shot in the head.
I saw it. I saw the blood, I...
I saw your body.
- Want to see it again?
- Shut up, Jack!
This is so wrong.
Tell me...what happened.
You were dead.
Clearly, I wasn't.
I was playing dead.
Then I cleared out.
- I went to Los Angeles.
- No, I saw you dead.
But I'm alive.
Feel.
You wanted to learn the secrets?
This is the best secret of all.
You're alive.
I'm alive.
I came back, Angelo.
I came back for you. Believe me,
I have never done that before.
I... I even got us that same old room.
You came back for me?
Yes. Yes, I did.
You don't know whether to hit me
or to kiss me, do you?
Come on,
you can try both.
(DOG BARKS, SIRENS WAIL)
What the hell, Angelo?
What did you do?
Il diavolo!
I am not the devil.
It's the only way.
The devil seduces with confidence.
No. No!
- Stay away from me, devil!
- Ah!
Ah! God!
(HE GASPS, SHE SCREAMS)
- Il diavolo! Il diavolo!
- Jack...
Il diavolo!
Ah!
I don't understand. Angelo,
I don't understand. What did he do?
- We can show you.
- É un miracolo.
A miracle?
I want to see. Do it again.
(SPEAKS ITALIAN)
JACK: No.
No.
(SPEAKS ITALIAN)
(GASPS)
- (CROWD GASPS)
- Diavolo!
Angelo...
Angelo!
Don't go!
(JACK SCREAMS)
MAN: I don't know.
I just don't know what it is.
Hmm. How much is the butcher asking?
1 0,000. Not too much for something
with so much potential.
And we'd own him...together?
A partnership. What do you say?
Agreed.
This is it.
It's been a long time coming.
All those years.
What's the most beautiful thing
you've ever seen? Not just on Earth.
I'm not doing this,
I'm not giving final speeches.
Just tell me,
anywhere in the universe.
I saw a firebird once,
a tiny little thing,
even smaller than a hummingbird.
- Oh?
- Literally made of fire.
It only lives for a minute.
It blazes different colours...and sings.
It gets so bright
you have to close your eyes.
And when you open them, it's gone.
But the image stays behind your eyelids
for longer than it was alive.
Tell me another one.
- I've said enough.
- No, go on, tell me.
Just tell me about your life,
all the things that you've never said.
How many children did you have, Jack?
I've lived a lot of lifetimes, Gwen,
I can't tell you everything.
A lot of lifetimes.
That's a consolation, isn't it? Is it?
When you've had
more lives than anyone...
It's not enough.
- I don't want to die.
- I know.
I'm so sorry, Jack.
It just...
It went crazy, like...like bloodlust.
I was so scared.
Are you going to take the wrist strap?
I'm a good thief.
I could have taken it any night.
You'd better clean up.
We've got to go. Can you stand?
Give me a minute.
I bought some inattention from Nico,
the guy who's supposed to be
watching you,
but it won't last for ever.
You can put these on.
Who were the three men?
What men?
There were three men.
Like they were making...
an agreement.
I don't know. Hurry up.
ANGELO: Hurry,
there's a train out tonight!
Train where? Where are we going?
Like you said, we'll go to the West Coast,
Los Angeles, together.
Jack!
Where are you going?
I left something here.
You left something in a vent on a roof?
Ha! Never go far without it.
- OK, but now we go.
- I'm going, yeah.
Time to move on.
But not with you.
I'm sorry.
I was terrified, Jack.
They said you were the devil,
but other people said
you were a blessing...
Something happened to me once,
a long way away.
Time itself changed me
to a...fixed point. And now I can't die.
I suffer and I perish...
...but I always come back.
I've lived through a lot of Earth's past
and a lot of its future.
And I'll keep on
living this life for ever.
- In the future, are we together?
- What does it matter?
- Are we together?
- We can't be,
cos one day you're going to die
- and I won't.
- Then we forget the future.
We make the moment now.
- We make a promise and we go forward.
- Angelo,
- don't.
- What? You're lonely, too.
You said you want a companion.
- Don't make me do this.
- You're not going without me!
- Just let me go.
- But you can't!
I'm never going to let you go.
I could travel this whole wide world,
but where would I find
another man like you?
Please, don't leave me on my own.
I'm sorry, Angelo,
but this is the story of my life.
It always ends the same way.
You kill me.
Men like you...
- ...you kill me.
- No!
No! No!
No! Jack!
- Know her?
- No.
- OK.
- WOMAN: Thank you.
You followed the instructions,
as far as I can tell.
Captain Harkness,
the last mortal man.
It has been a long journey.
- (GUNSHOT)
- What the hell?!
- Find out who that is!
- It's on you.
Who is it?
What the hell are they doing?!
(GUN COCKS)
Gotcha.
Bad day, Gwen?
(BEEPING)
- Rex.
- Yeah?
Rex, you gotta see this.
I was just checking the cache
on the I-5s. Look what it says.
- Can we track them?
- Yes.
Oh, Gwen!
- You ready?
- I'm ready.
Must be Rex and Esther.
- She's still got Anwen.
- Not for long.
Uh, you've got a little something
on you there.
Now unless you want to be
diagnosed Category 1 ...
Put your guns down.
OK, get back! Get back! Back!
- Her hands are up.
- Yes.
Go, go, go!
- All right, go, go, go!
- (THEY SHOUT ORDERS)
Grid one! Check him out!
One down. Living room clear.
Spread out, follow the grid.
Yes, sir. Jackson, with me.
Rhys, I can't believe it. We got you,
don't worry. You're all right.
Took your bloody time!
Yes, I know, Mrs Cooper.
It's been frantic.
We got this call. I was off duty...
Gun, gun, gun!
I've never shot anyone before.
Where's Gwen?
Andy! What's happened to Gwen?
It's OK. It's OK.
Your family and baby, they're safe.
Next time, just ask for help. I'm sick
of Torchwood acting like amateur clowns.
Oh, you did it! Thank you!
Got it?
Thank you.
And you, you're going to live.
It's a talent of mine.
I meant every word I said.
- So did I.
- Good.
And as for you...
you'd better pray
that death comes back to this planet
by the time I'm finished with you.
So tell us who you are,
before I let her loose.
I don't see that anything's changed.
You're still coming with me.
- Why would I do that?
- You'll want to come with me
because I can take you to the one man
who knows how the miracle began.
- Who's that?
- Angelo.
Angelo Colasanto.
He's waiting for you, Jack.
He's been waiting
for such a very long time.
They don't exist.
- Shit!
- What is it, Rex?
Everybody, stay where you are!
Back down.
OK, OK, all right.
- Leave me alone with him.
- (GRUNTS)
- Goddamn it!
- Shit.
While you were wasting time, Mr Shapiro,
we've got the names of the people
who are responsible
for causing the miracle.
I suggest we get to work.
He's preaching hellfire and salvation,
which makes Oswald Danes
the most popular man in the world
right now.
Get me a girl.
How old?
Mr Danes?
I can act all kinds of innocent.
Don't presume to know me.
I am capable of far more
than my...reputation.
(GIGGLES)
I said...don't presume.
Actually, if you don't mind,
I think I'd like to go.
Don't! Don't you dare!
This is like the whole world
is changing...
...and we're just so tiny.
There's a reason why Torchwood was secret.
We kept things hidden from the human race.
This technology is a science
the world should never know.
This thing would be the end of us.